National Arts Club
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
National Arts Club records
1898-1960
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
National Arts Club
32.25 linear feet
The records of the National Arts Club measure 32.25 linear feet and date from 1898 to 1960. The collection documents the founding of the club, and it's governance, administration, exhibitions, and social activities
Historical Note
The National Arts Club was founded by Charles de Kay, literary and art critic for the New York Times who believed there was a need for a club uniting all of the arts. In March of 1898, de Kay called together a number of civic leaders and men prominent in the art world who supported the idea, elected the first officers and incorporated the Club in 1899.
As stated in a circular issued by the Club, its specified purposes were: to promote the mutual acquaintance of art lovers and art workers in the United States; to stimulate and guide toward practical and artistic expression the artistic sense of the American people; to maintain in the City of New York a Club House...for social purposes in connection with the arts; to provide proper exhibition facilities for such lines of art, especially applied and industrial art, as shall not be otherwise adequately provided for in the same City; and to encourage the publication and circulation of news, suggestions and discussions relating to the fine arts.
During its initial months, the National Arts Club operated from a temporary office at 156 Fifth Avenue. In the search for a permanent site, considerable care was taken to select an auspicious location and accommodations, and in 1899 the first clubhouse was opened at 37 West 34th Street in leased quarters renovated expressly for the Club. Within a year, the gallery and restaurant required additional space, and there was a desire to provide overnight quarters for members visiting from out of town. In 1901 the Club created a corporation, Arts Realty Co., which issued shares to members and other investors for the purpose of raising funds to purchase the adjacent property (39 West 34th Street). This end was accomplished, and when it was decided to move the Club to another location, proceeds from the sale of the lease on 37 West 34th Street and the lot next door, augmented by additional funds subscribed by members, enabled Arts Realty Co. to acquire the Tilden Mansion at 15 Gramercy Park in 1905. Construction was begun immediately on a connecting studio tower to the rear (119-121 East 19th Street), designed by architect and Club President George B. Post. Upon completion, the Club bought the property from Arts Realty Co., issuing both First and Second Mortgage Bonds to individual subscribers. The Gramercy Park property has been occupied by the Club since 1906.
A show of American gold and silver work in October 1899 was the first exhibition held at the National Arts Club. Decorative arts, crafts, and industrial arts figured prominently in early exhibitions, as did designs for civic improvements. The monthly exhibition schedule emphasized contemporary American art, but also included some historical shows. Members of the public were admitted without charge to the galleries, where they could view such innovative and important exhibitions as Pictorial Photographs presented by the Photo-Secession (1902) and a group exhibition featuring the works of Robert Henri, William Glackens, George Luks, Arthur B. Davies, and Maurice Prendergast (1904). After about 1907, exhibitions grew more conservative, probably reflecting the personal tastes of Art Committee members rather than a formal opposition of the Club to nonrepresentational art. Increasingly, the exhibition schedule was filled by shows of members' work, the Club's permanent collection (mainly works by artist members, usually given in payment for life membership), the Annual Arts and Crafts exhibitions, Books of the Year exhibitions, and shows organized by various art societies.
In addition to exhibitions, the National Arts Club regularly featured a variety of cultural programs such as concerts, lectures, and dramatic presentations for members and guests. Parties, dinner, dances, and other social activities drew members to the Club, too. During its first years, some artist members expressed dissatisfaction with the high priority given social functions; by 1905, J. Carroll Beckwith, Walter Shirlaw, and Stanford White were among those who had resigned for this reason.
Within the National Arts Club there have been some smaller societies. The earliest of these were The Discus, a short lived dining and debating club, and The Vagabonds, a lunch group of writers, editors, printers and illustrators. The Men's Open Table, founded in 1910, met weekly for more than forty years for dinner followed by a talk, given by a fellow member or an outside, often professional, lecturer. A wide range of topics, not necessarily on the arts, were presented and discussed at the Men's Open Table. The American Institute of Graphic Arts is one of the organizations said to have developed from associations formed and discussions held at the Men's Open Table. A Women's Open Table, patterned after the men's, was established later.
The National Arts Club, unlike many other private clubs founded during the same era, admitted women members from its inception. Throughout its history, the Club's membership has been comprised of artists, musicians, writers, and performers, as well as collectors and supporters of the arts drawn from all parts of the country. Membership peaked at around 1,800 in 1920, declining throughout the Depression and again in the mid-1950s, and remaining at about 600 for the next two decades.
Date Event
1898 Founding; occupied temporary office at 156 Fifth Ave.
1899 Incorporation; leased clubhouse at 37 West 34th St.; opened first exhibition, American Gold and Silver Work
1900 Constitution adopted
1901 First donations to permanent collection; Arts Realty Co. formed for the purpose of acquiring and financing the adjacent property (39 West 34th St.)
1905 Arts Realty Co. purchased Gramercy Park property (Tilden Mansion) on behalf of NAC; remodeling of clubhouse and construction of studio tower begun
1906 Plan for financing new clubhouse approved; second Mortgage Bonds issued; clubhouse and studio tower occupied; First Annual Books of the Year Exhibition
1907 Annual Members' Exhibition initiated; Bulletin began publication
1910 First meeting of Men's Open Table (established 1909)
1914 Essay contest, "A Critical Estimate of the Altman Collection"
1917 American Artists War Emergency Fund Committee issues art stamp
1923 Junior Artist membership category created
1930-1931 Essay contest, "Soul of America"
1940 Works by deceased artist life members deaccessioned from permanent collection; fund for refugee artists established
1962 Clubhouse designated New York City Landmark
1976 Clubhouse designated National Historic Landmark
1987 NAC records donated to Archives of American Art
Scope and Content Note
Records of the National Arts Club, spanning the period 1898 to 1960, document the founding of the organization, and its governance, administration, finances, exhibitions, and social activities. There are large gaps in the records and many of those surviving are incomplete, which can be explained by a 1932 resolution of the Board of Governors that "old files and letters and bills in the storeroom prior to 1922 may be destroyed at the discretion of the Secretary and Treasurer."
Minutes and reports of the Board of Governors and Executive Committee are fairly complete through 1949, but sparse thereafter. Records do not exist for all standing and special committees, and those remaining tend to be concentrated in the early twentieth century.
Correspondence of the officers, for the most part, is routine and relates to administrative matters. Financial records cover the period 1917 to 1950, with a large number of gaps.
A small number of records of the Arts Realty Co. (later known as 15 Gramercy Park, Inc.) are extant. These include lists of stockholders, correspondence concerning mortgage bonds, and minutes.
Membership records, arranged alphabetically, are available for the years 1931 to 1959, and there are rosters arranged by membership category, 1940-1952; in addition, printed membership lists were issued circa 1900-1951.
More than four hundred exhibitions are known to have been held in the galleries of the National Arts Club between 1899 and 1960. Catalogs for 124 National Arts Club exhibitions are available at the Archives of American Art; 69 titles are to be found among the Club's records and an additional 55 were microfilmed previously as parts of other collections. Other exhibition documentation includes printed matter such as invitations, entry blanks, publicity, and photographs (see Appendix A). For some exhibitions, supporting documentation such as correspondence with exhibitors and collectors, sales and consignment records, and shipping receipts have survived. These files are mainly confined to Books of the Year exhibitions, Arts and Crafts/Decorative Arts exhibitions, and a smaller number of exhibitions of Living American Etchers, 1928-1957.
General social events, activities sponsored by Arts Club committees, and special commemorative occasions are documented by invitations, programs, publicity, calendars of events, and photographs. The majority of this material is contained in seventeen scrapbooks, 1898-1940. Programs of the Men's Open Table, 1915-1950, are particularly well documented by the Chairman's correspondence and three volumes containing meeting notices with signatures of members in attendance.
In addition to printed matter relating to exhibitions and events, scrapbooks, 1898-1940, contain general publicity, clippings concerning members, and samples of National Arts Club printed matter such as form letters to the general membership, brochures, ballots, house rules, published membership lists, year books, and the like. Loose printed matter augments that preserved in the scrapbooks. These sources combined provide a fairly complete set of the Bulletin, but the number of year books is small, and there are catalogs of only slightly more than a third of the exhibitions identified.
Photographs, in addition to those recording exhibitions and events, include portraits of governors, officers, distinguished visitors, speakers, and performers; views of Gramercy Park and the interior and exterior of the clubhouse; and works of art in the permanent collection.
Miscellaneous material includes information on the National Arts Club's first home on West 34th Street, and the Tilden Mansion, its current clubhouse on Gramercy Park; histories of the organization; unpublished speeches presented at Club occasions; and copies of legal documents, including the Club's charter and act of incorporation.
See index 1 for A List of National Arts Club Exhibitions
See index 2 for List of Officers of the National Arts Club
Arrangement
The records are arranged into the following series:
Series 1: Board of Governors, 1898-1960, undated
Series 2: Administration, 1898-1960, undated
Series 3: Financial Records, 1917-1952
Series 4: Membership, circa 1900-1962
Series 5: Arts Realty Co., 1909-1913, 1945-1956, undated
Series 6: Miscellaneous, 1890-1961, undated
Series 7: Photographs, 1899-1957, undated
Series 8: Printed Matter, 1893-1960, undated
Series 9: Scrapbooks, 1898-1940
Related Material
These citations were compiled from Art Index, 1929-1960; The New York Times Index, 1898-1960; Poole's Index to Periodical Literature, 1898-1906; Nineteenth Century Readers' Guide to Periodical Literature, 1898-1899; and Readers' Guide to Periodical Literature, 1900-1960, using the format employed in Art Index. Citations are presented in chronological order, as it is anticipated that most researchers consulting the National Arts Club Records will be interested in a specific event or era in the Club's history, or are apt to be researching artists whose National Arts Club affiliation or exhibition activities were confined to a particular period.
1898
National Art Club. Harpers Weekly 42:329, April 2.
1899
Club to advance art industries. Critic 34:349-51, April.
National Arts Club organized. New York Times (7-2), 29-288-2, April 26.
1909
Position as a factor in the encouragement of the fine arts. G. Teall. Craftsman 15:604-13, February.
Club officials rule a member may take a process server into club as a guest to serve papers on fellow member, case of R.S. Perrin vs. D. Whipple. New York Times 7:3, June 29.
1913
Lecture of Prof. Eucken on Art and Morality. New York Times 9:3, March 1.
Offers prize to member who writes best manuscript on "A Critical Estimate of the Altman Collection." New York Times 12:7, November 8.
Annual exhibition of Books of the Year; organization of American Institute of Graphic Arts planned. New York Times 9:3, November 13.
1914
Alexander de Yourevitch has visited Russian political exiles as agent from the Czar; arranges for Russian trade exhibit in New York; National Arts Club has agreed to cooperate. New York Times 20:2, March 27.
Dinner in honor of Shakespeare celebration, address by Henry Clews. New York Times 13:2, April 24.
Farewell dinner to Karl Vollmoeller and George Sylvester Viereck at National Arts Club by Alfred Rau. New York Times III, 7:3, May 7.
Exhibition of Books of the Year (editorial). New York Times VI, 514:2, November 22.
1915
Awards announced. New York Times 10:1, January 7.
Paintings exhibition. New York Times V, 11:13, January 10.
Poster exhibition. New York Times III, 2:5, March 28.
Thanksgiving dinner to east side waifs. New York Times 11:1, November 26.
1917
Annual exhibition; Gold Medal and $1000 prize awarded to Ben Foster. New York Times 10:6, January 4.
Memorial services for W.B. Howland. New York Times 7:3, March 3.
Offers prizes for best patriotic medal, poem, and song. New York Times 9:14, April 6.
Offers prizes to promote expression of American patriotism in art. New York Times IV, 13:2, April 15.
H.A.W. Wood speaks at distribution of prizes. New York Times 11:3, May 31.
"Road to France," $500 prize offered for appropriate music. New York Times 13:2, June 9.
American Artists' War Emergency Fund Committee announces that art stamp will be sold to aid artists reduced in circumstances through the war. New York Times 13:6, July 10.
Offers prize of $500 for best musical setting for D.M. Henderson's "The Road to France." New York Times VIII, 9:3, August 12.
Prize for music for war song by D.M. Henderson is awarded to Signe Lund. New York Times 13:3, November 1.
1919
Annual books exhibition. New York Times VIII, 686:1, November 23.
1921
Comment on suggestion by G. Bellows that proposed members should possess some work by living American artist. New York Times III, 20:3, February 6.
Elects governors. New York Times 9:2, April 13.
1922
Awards Agar prize to Christine Herter. New York Times 16:7, April 7.
Address by Ann Martin. New York Times 4:3, August 3.
1923
Annual exhibition of books; I. Zangwill speaks; protest by member. New York Times 6:1, November 8.
1924
Prize winners of annual exhibition. New York Times 4:15, January 10.
Honors J.G. Agar at dinner. New York Times 6:2, February 26.
1925
Mural panels of Old NY used for New Year's fete to be put on exhibition. New York Times 29:1, January 4.
Announces prize winners at Members' Annual Exhibition. New York Times VIII, 11:2, January 18.
Murals depicting history of NYC, painted for New Years' ball, to be given to Museum of the City of New York. New York Times 25:4, February 3.
Exhibition of lithographs, woodcuts, and linoleum prints. New York Times VIII, 11:13, April 12.
1926
Exhibition. New York Times 4:5, January 14.
Exhibition. New York Times 17:3, April 8.
Exhibition of photographs of recent buildings. New York Times VIII, 12:6, April 18.
15th century books brought from Germany by Dr. Otto H.F. Vollbehr on exhibition at the National Arts Club. New York Times 6:6, August 24.
15th century Book of Hours, worth $15,000, stolen from exhibition at National Arts Club. New York Times 1:2, August 26.
Feature article on exhibition. New York Times IV, 15:1, August 29.
Book of Hours mysteriously returned to Vollbehr by E.M. Garlock, attorney, acting for unnamed client who claims to have bought book from stranger. New York Times 19:1, September 12.
Editorial on return of book. New York Times 20:4, September 13.
21st annual book exhibit; addresses. New York Times 28:3, November 4.
History in connection with 20th anniversary celebration. New York Times VIII,18:6, November 7.
1927
New Year's Eve costume ball. New York Times 15:3, January 1.
Exhibition of American paintings. New York Times 25:5, March 3.
Exhibition of etchings. New York Times IX, 10:4, December 11.
1928
Exhibits. New York Times 30:2, January 12; New York Times IX, 13:2, January 29.
Awards in small painting exhibition. New York Times 27:2, February 10.
Exhibit. New York Times VIII, 15:3, February 12.
First exhibition of decorative arts. New York Times 28:4, March 15; New York Times IX, 15:4, March 18.
Exhibition. New York Times IX, 15:2, April 15.
1929
J. Lie, P. Manship, and C. Beach win prizes. New York Times 25:3, January 11.
Annual members' exhibition. New York Times X, 18:4, January 27.
Exhibition of crafts. New York Times X, 15:6, December 8.
Prize awarded to D.C. Nisbet. New York Times 23:5, December 29.
1930
Arts Club prizes announced. Art News 28:21, January 4.
Annual exhibition of painting and sculpture. New York Times VIII, 13:3, January 19.
Seventh annual exhibition. New York Times VIII, 13:1, February 16.
Annual junior art show. New York Times 3:5, March 15; New York Times X, 19:3, March 16.
Exhibition of prints by living American etchers. New York Times X, 18:1, December 14.
1931
New York season; Living American Etchers. Art Digest 5:14, January 1.
M. Gregg Memorial Prize awarded to I.G. Olinsky; medal to H.W. Watrous. New York Times 34:6, January 10.
Exhibitions. New York Times VIII, 12:7, February 22.
Exhibition of Junior Artist Members. New York Times IX, 13:4, March 15.
Hold exhibition of portraits and other objects relating to history of Gramercy Park. New York Times II, 1:7 and 18:4, May 3.
Annual exhibition of paintings by members. New York Times 30:6, June 4.
Awards to R.D. Bowden $3000 prize, offered by J.G. Agar for best book on "The Soul of America." New York Times 20:6, June 8.
1932
Annual exhibition of work by painter and sculptor members; prizes announced. New York Times 27:7, January 7.
Art Club prizes. Art Digest 6:10, January 15.
Forum on development of art talent in young artists. New York Times 13:8, January 18.
Arts Club prizes. Art News 30:20, January 23.
Opening. New York Times 16:7, February 4.
Prizes awarded to junior artists. New York Times 19:2, March 8.
Art auction totals $600. New York Times 19:5, April 14.
Members' exhibition of small paintings. New York Times 16:6, May 5.
National Arts Club book exhibition. E. Yost. Publishers Weekly 122:2382-3, December 31.
1933
R. Nickerson, new member, wins medal at annual painting and sculpture show; other awards. New York Times 18:2, January 5.
Annual members' exhibition. New York Times 13:2, January 13; New York Times IX, 12:6, January 15.
National Arts club prizes. Art Digest 7:15, January 15; Art News 31:7, January 28 Celebrates 119th birthday of S.J. Tilden. New York Times 17:6, February 8.
Exhibition by junior artist members. New York Times 15:2, March 2.
1934
Prizes for annual members' show announced. New York Times IX, 12:3, January 14.
Annual dinner. New York Times 17:4, January 18.
Prizes. Art Digest February 1, 8:19; Art Digest 8:13, May 15.
Memorial exhibition of eight of its deceased painter and sculptor members. New York Times IX, 12:6, February 4.
Junior members exhibit. New York Times 17:1, March 8; New York Times IX, 9:7, March 18; Prizes awarded. New York Times 22:8, March 22.
Annual members' show. New York Times 17:2, May 3; Awards, New York Times 21:1, May 8; New York Times IX, 7:7, May 13.
Awards given by Arts Club. Art News 32:4, June 2.
Rare book exhibition planned. New York Times 19:4, September 18; Exhibition. New York Times 17:1, September 19.
1935
Annual exhibition of members' work opened. New York Times 17:5, January 10; New York Times 9:3, January 14.
Annual dinner; awards. New York Times 20:7, January 17.
Stag dinner; portrait of Victoria replaces painting of nude. New York Times 23:4, February 1.
Prizes, annual exhibition of painting and sculpture. Art Digest 9:21, February 1.
Members' annual exhibition. New York Times 18:2, February 8; New York Times VIII, 9:6, February 17.
Annual exhibition by junior artists. New York Times 18:5, March 9.
Arts Club plans a large bazaar. Art News 33:10, August 17.
Series of articles on traditions of club being written. New York Times II, 7:1, October 6.
Plans for annual book week. New York Times II and III, 8:5, October 13; exhibitors to be entertained by J.R. Gregg, president. New York Times 19:2, October 30.
To award two trips to Europe for mural decoration. New York Times 26:7, November 1; New York Times 19:5, November 14.
To hold "At Home" tea. New York Times II, 8:2, December 8.
Dinner. New York Times 14:8, December 11.
1936
Annual members' exhibition. New York Times 19:6, January 9; New York Times 13:8, January 11; New York Times IX, 10:1, January 19.
Exhibition of modern textbooks. New York Times 17:7, February 6.
Announces winners of trips to Europe. New York Times 21:2, February 11.
Exhibition by neighboring organizations. New York Times IX, 8:1, April 12.
Summer exhibit from permanent collection. New York Times IX, 7:4, June 21.
Exhibition of contemporary books; authors' night. New York Times VI, 9:2, November 8.
Plans for children's matinee at annual book exhibition. New York Times VI, 7:2, November 8.
Women's open table plans dinner. New York Times 16:4, November 23.
Exhibition of Society of American Etchers. New York Times XII, 9:2, November 29.
1937
Awards at members' exhibit. New York Times 24:3, January 27.
Exhibitions sponsored by Society of American Etchers. New York Times 21:3, February 3; New York Times X, 9:7, February 7.
Women's committee holds drama dinner. New York Times 13:1, February 15.
R.D. Kohn speaks, New York Times 25:7, March 11.
Jr. artists group exhibit. New York Times IX, 10:1, March 14; Awards. New York Times 23:6, March 25.
Photographic exhibition. New York Times X, 10:2, May 16.
Officers elected. New York Times 19:1, May 20.
H. Hamilton exhibit. New York Times IX, 6:7, September 26.
Book of the year exhibit. New York Times 23:6, November 4; New York Times VI, 4:3, November 28.
Mr. H.P. Crine elected life member. New York Times 9:1, November 28.
Members' exhibit. New York Times 28:3, December 9.
1938
Women's Open Table plans. New York Times 11:2, January 17.
Members' annual exhibit. New York Times, January 18 26:2; New York Times IX,9:3, January 23; Awards. New York Times 22:2, January 27.
Members studio receptions planned. New York Times VI, 2:7, January 30.
Dinner honoring Dr. W. Damrosch. New York Times 12:5, March 7.
Exhibit by art groups near NYC. New York Times 20:8, March 28.
Group show. New York Times X, 8:2, April 17.
Viennese ball. New York Times 22:6, April 21.
J.F. Talcott elected president; D.E. Waid executive committee chairman. New York Times 21:6, November 19.
Victorian ball. New York Times 18:1, December 17.
1939
Members' memorial exhibit. New York Times 15:1, January 13; New York Times IX, 9:2, January 22.
Members' painting and sculpture exhibit. New York Times IX, 9:2, February 5.
Jr. Members' lecture. New York Times 10:2, February 6.
Painting exhibit. New York Times 18:1, March 1; New York Times X, 10:2, March 5.
Jr. Members party planned. New York Times 50:3, March 5.
Exhibit of neighboring art organizations. New York Times 13:2, April 17.